<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-msri-grow-bmp-compression-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BMP compression">BMP Compression</title>

    <author fullname="Mukul Srivastava" initials="M." surname="Srivastava">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Technology Park Drive</street>

          <city>Westford MA</city>

          <code>01886</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>msri@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paolo Lucente" initials="P." surname="Lucente">
      <organization>NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Siriusdreef 70-72</street>

          <city>Hoofddorp</city>

          <region>WT</region>

          <code>2132</code>

          <country>Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>paolo@ntt.net</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="15" month="October" year="2019"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides specification for an optional compressed BMP
      Feed from a router to BMP station. </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>
    <xref target="RFC8174">RFC 8174</xref> when, and only when, they
    appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The BGP Monitoring Protocol (BMP) allows monitoring of 
      Rib-in <xref target="RFC7854">RFC7854</xref>, 
      Loc-Rib,<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-local-rib">BGP local-rib</xref> and
      Rib-in and Rib-Out monitoring allows pre-policy and post-policy view of the prefix.
      Thus, for a scaled setup, with all these kinds of monitoring enabled,
      BMP will get a lot of back pressure in the protocol as it needs to dump a huge data 
      for its monitored peers, through a single socket towards BMP station.
      BGP update PDU which is part of the BMP Route-monitoring (RM) message is also increasing.
      It is no more limited to 4K as noted in draft-ietf-idr-bgp-extended-messages-21. 
      Essentially, BMP is heading towards becoming I/O bound monitoring protocol.
      This document proposes compression of BMP feed towards BMP station. Compression will ease the
      pressure on TCP socket between a router and BMP station. 
      Such a scheme would be useful if a route can spare some extra CPU for BMP operation. </t>

      <t>As it must be obvious, this scheme will require compressor mechanism at the BMP speaking
         router and a decompressor on the BMP station. The compression mechanism used at the BMP 
        speaking is an implementation specific detail and is beyond the scope of this specification. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Procedures">

      <section title="Starting Compressor Capability">

        <t>BMP compression feature on the router and BMP decompressor feature on the BMP station
           has to be present at the same time. Enabling compression feature at router end only will lead to 
           incomprehensible data at the BMP station end. Also same technique should be used to compress and
           decompress the data on wire. Using different technique to compress and decompress would lead to 
           incomprehensible data at the BMP station end.</t>

        <t>BMP compression feature on the router and BMP decompressor feature on the BMP station can be 
           enabled via configuraton. Once this feature is enabled between router and BMP station, the 
           monitored router should indicate this to the BMP Station using new Compression Information TLV 
           as described in following section. </t>

        <t>From that point onwards, the router would send the compressed BMP feed towards BMP station. 
           BMP session needs to be bounced every-time this feature is enabled on a current active BMP session.</t>

      </section>


      <section title="Compression Information TLV" anchor="tlv">

        <t>As noted in <xref target="RFC7854">RFC7854</xref>, the initiation message provides a 
           means for the monitored router to inform the monitoring station of its vendor specific
           details. It can carry Information TLVs containing information about the monitored router. </t>
  
        <t>The monitored router MUST communicate the compression capability to BMP staton using
           Compression Information TLV described below.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
| Information Type (2 octets)   |     Length (2 octets)         |
+-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
| CM | CMINFO |                Reserved                         |                
+---------------------------------------------------------------+


                  Figure 1: Compression Information TLV]]></artwork>
        </figure><list style="symbols">
          <t>Type = TDB1 (2 Octets): Compression Information TLV type.</t>

          <t>Length (2 Octets): indicates the length of the value field of the
          Compression Information TLV. The value field further consists of the 
          Compression string.</t> 


          <t>CM (4 bits): CM indicating DEFLATE compressed format value
             as specified in RFC1950.</t>

         <t> CINFO (4 bits): INFO as specified in RFC1950. 
            Invalid values MUST lead to the
            capability being ignored. The compressing peer MUST use this value 
            for the parametrization of its algorithm.</t>

        </list></t>


      </section>


      <section title="Compressed BMP Messages" anchor="message">

        <t> Following rules should be following for achieving BMP feed compression:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="numbers"> 

	    <t> A new message type, Compressed Route Monitoring (CRM), MUST be used. This is
		to ensure backward compatibility with BMP stations that do not support the
		compression capability. The message type is same in structure as described
		by <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">TLV support for BMP Route
		Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref>. Compression is to be applied only
		to this message type, all other BMP message types shall not be compressed.</t>
  
            <t> Compression is applicable to all the payload following the Common Header,
		described in <xref target="RFC7854">Section 4.1 of</xref>. This allows to
		read the total BMP message length, i.e. to perform sanity checks against
		socket and compressor information.</t>

            <t> Each compressed BMP message MUST be sent as a block, i.e. the decompression
		MUST be able to yield decompressed results of the without waiting for further
		compressed updates. This is different from the normally used stream compression
		mode.</t>

            <t> The compressed message MAY exceed the maximum message size but in such 
		case compressor overflow per <xref format="default" pageno="false"
		target="overflow"/> MUST be invoked.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>


      <section title="Compressor Overflow" anchor="overflow">
            <t> This should be handled in same was as described in
		<xref target="I-D.przygienda-idr-compressed-updates">draft-przygienda-idr-compressed-updates</xref>. 
	    </t>
      </section>


      <section title="Error Handling" anchor="error">
          <t> If the decompression on the BMP station fails for any reason, 
              it needs to bring down the BMP session. </t>

          <t> If the compression on the monitoring router fails for any reason, 
              it is at the discretion of the router to handle it. It may try it few more times.
              In the worse case it MAY bring down the BMP session</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Processing of Compressed Route Monitoring messages" anchor="decompression">
            <t> A BMP station receiving a compressed message SHOULD process it
		as follows:</t>

	    <t>
		<list style="numbers"> 
		<t>Decode the BMP Common Header where message length is specified</t>
		<t>Decompress remainder of the Compressed Route Monitoring message and
		   determine the decompressed message size from the decompressor</t>
		<t>Decode the BMP Per-peer header</t>
		<t>Decode the BGP UPDATE PDU header to infer the presence of trailing TLVs</t>
		<t>Decode the BMP message TLVs</t>
		<t>Decode the actual BGP UPDATE PDU</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
      </section>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t> This document requests that IANA assign the following new parameters
      to the BMP parameters name space.</t>

      <section title="BMP Compression Information TLV">
        <t>This document defines the BMP Compression Information TLV Header with Type = TBD
        (<xref target="tlv"/>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="BMP Compression Route Monitoring message type">
        <t>This document also defines the BMP Compressed Route Monitoring message type with
	Type = TBD (<xref target="message"/>).</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t> It is not believed that this document adds any additional security
      considerations.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7854'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-local-rib'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.przygienda-idr-compressed-updates'?>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
